<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Queenie</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Publication Information</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
      <body>
        <p>Queenie said, ‘Maybe you better stop calling me that,’ and I said,
                ‘What?’</p>
        <p>‘Stan
                doesn’t like it,’ she said. ‘Queenie.’</p>
        <p>It was a
                worse surprise to me to hear her say ‘Stan’ than to have her tell me to call her by
                her right name, which was Lena. But I could hardly expect her to go on calling him
                Mr Vorguilla, now that they were married, and had been for nearly two years.
                During that time I hadn’t seen her, and for a moment when I saw her in the
                group of people waiting for the train at Union Station, I hadn’t recognised
                her. Her hair was dyed black, and puffed up around her face in whatever style it
                was that in those days succeeded the beehive. Its beautiful corn-syrup colour -
                gold on top and dark underneath - as well as its silky length, was for ever
                lost. She wore a yellow print dress that skimmed her body and ended inches
                above her knees. The Cleopatra lines drawn heavily around her eyes, and the
                purply shadow, made her eyes seem smaller, not larger, as if they
                were deliberately hiding. She had pierced ears now, gold hoops swinging from
                them.</p>
        <p>I hadn’t
                known what to say to her. I saw her look at me with some surprise as well. I tried
                to be bold and easy-going. I said, ‘Is that a dress or a frill around your bum?’ She
                laughed, and I said, ‘Was it ever hot on the train, I’m sweating like a pig.’ I
                could hear my own loud voice, as twangy and vulgar as Bet’s. Sweating like a
                pig.</p>
        <p>Now on the
                streetcar going to Lena’s place I couldn’t stop the stupidity. I said, ‘Are we still
                downtown?’ The high buildings had been quickly left behind
                but I didn’t think you could call this area residential. The same thing went on
                over and over again - a dry cleaner, a florist, a grocery store, a restaurant.
                Boxes of fruit and vegetables out on the sidewalk, signs for dentists
                and dressmakers and plumbing suppliers in the second-storey windows. Hardly a
                building higher than that, hardly a tree.</p>
        <p>‘It’s not
                the real downtown,’ said Queenie. ‘Remember I showed you where Simpson’s was? Where
                we got on the streetcar? That’s the real.’</p>
        <p>‘So are we
                nearly there?’ I said.</p>
        <p>She said,
                ‘We got a ways to go yet.’ Then she said, ‘Way. Stan doesn’t like me saying “ways”
                either. The trouble with Queenie, he says it reminds him of a horse.’</p>
        <p>The
                repetition of things, or maybe the heat, was making me feel anxious and slightly
                sick. We were holding my suitcase on our knees and only a couple of inches ahead of
                my fingers was a man’s fat neck and bald head. Just a few black, rather long
                hairs grew out of his head here and there, and they made me feel like throwing
                up. For some reason I thought of Mr Vorguilla’s teeth in the medicine cabinet.
                Two teeth sitting beside his razor and shaving-brush and the wooden bowl
                holding his possibly hairy and disgusting shaving-soap. I had looked in the medicine
                cabinet when it wasn’t any of my business and I brought Queenie in and showed
                her.</p>
        <p>‘I know,’
                she said. ‘It’s his bridge.’</p>
        <p>‘Why isn’t
                he wearing them?’</p>
        <p>‘He is.
                He’s wearing his others. These are his spares.’</p>
        <p>‘Yuck,’ I
                said. ‘Aren’t they yellow?’</p>
        <p>‘Shut up,’ said Queenie. But she was
                laughing.</p>
        <p>Mrs Vorguilla was lying on the dining-room
                couch with her eyes shut, but maybe not sleeping.</p>
        <p>‘What he doesn’t like about Queenie,’ Queenie
                said, ‘is he says it reminds him of a horse.’</p>
        <p>When we
                got off the streetcar at last we
                had to walk up a steep hill, trying awkwardly to share the weight of the suitcase.
                The houses were not quite all the same though at first they
                looked like it. Some of the roofs came down over the walls like caps, or
                else the whole second storey was like a roof, covered in shingles. The shingles
                were dark green or maroon or brown. The porches came to within a few feet of
                the sidewalk and the spaces between the houses seemed narrow enough for people
                to reach out the side windows and shake hands. Children were playing on the
                sidewalk, but Queenie took no more notice of them than if they were birds
                pecking in the cracks. A very fat man, naked from the waist up, sat on his front
                staring at us in such a fixed and gloomy way that I was sure he had something
                to say to us. But Queenie marched on past him.</p>
        <p>She turned
                in partway up the hill, following a gravel path between some garbage tins. Out of an
                upstairs window a woman called something that I found unintelligible. Queenie called
                back, ‘It’s just my sister, she’s visiting.’</p>
        <p>‘Our
                landlady,’ she said. ‘They live in the front and upstairs. They’re Greeks. She
                doesn’t speak hardly any English.’</p>
        <p>It turned
                out that Queenie and Mr Vorguilla shared a bathroom with the Greeks. You took your
                roll of toilet paper with you - if you forgot, there wasn’t any. I had to go in
                there at once, because I was menstruating heavily and had to change my pad. For
                years afterwards, the sight of certain city streets on hot days, certain shades
                of brown brick and dark-painted shingles, and the noise of streetcars, would
                bring back to me the memory of cramps low in the belly, waves of
                flushing, bodily leakage and confusion.</p>
        <p>There was
                one bedroom where Queenie slept with Mr Vorguilla, and another bedroom turned into a
                small living-room, and a narrow kitchen, and a sun porch. The cot in the sun porch
                was where I was to sleep. Close outside the windows the landlord and another
                man were fixing a motorcycle. The smell of oil, of metal and machinery mixed
                with the smell of ripe tomatoes in the sun. There was a radio blaring music out
                of an upstairs window.</p>
        <p>‘One thing
                Stan can’t stand’, said Queenie. ‘That radio.’ She pulled the flowered curtains
                close, but the noise and sun still came through. ‘I wish I could’ve afforded
                lining,’ she said.</p>
        <p>I had the
                old pad wrapped up in toilet paper, in my hand. She brought me a paper bag and
                directed me to the outdoor garbage pail. ‘Every one of them,’ she said. ‘Out there
                right away. You won’t forget, will you?’</p>
        <p>I still
                tried to be nonchalant, and act as if I felt welcome. ‘I need to get a nice cool
                dress like yours,’ I said.</p>
        <p>‘Maybe I
                could make you one,’ said Queenie, with her head in the fridge. ‘I want a Coke, do
                you? I just go to this place they sell remnants. I made this whole dress for around
                three dollars. What size are you now, anyway?’</p>
        <p>‘Fourteen,’
                I said. ‘But I’m trying to lose.’</p>
        <p>‘Still. We
                could maybe find something.’</p>
        <p>am going to marry a lady that has a little girl about your age,’ my
                father had said. ‘And this little girl has not got any father. So you have to
                promise me one thing and that is that you will never tease her or say anything
                mean to her about that. There’ll be times when you may get in a fight and
                disagree with each other the way sisters do but that is one thing you never
                must say. And if other kids say it you never take their side.’</p>
        <p>For the
                sake of argument, I said that I did not have a mother and nobody said anything mean
                to me.</p>
        <p>My father
                said, ‘That’s different’.</p>
        <p>He was
                wrong about everything. We did not seem anywhere near the same age, because Queenie
                was nine, when my father married Bet, and I was six. Though later, after I had
                skipped a grade and Queenie had failed one, we came closer together in school.
                And I never knew anyone to try to be mean to Queenie. She was somebody
                everybody wanted to be friends with. She was chosen first for a baseball team
                even though she was a careless baseball player, and first for a spelling
                team though she was a poor speller. Also, she and I did not get into fights.
                Not once. She showed plenty of kindness towards me and I had plenty of
                admiration for her. I would have worshipped her for her dark-gold hair and her
                sleepy-looking dark eyes and her giggly easy-going confidence, even if she had
                not been kind. But for a pretty girl she had an extraordinarily sweet
            nature.</p>
        <p>As soon as
                I woke up on the morning of Queenie’s disappearance, that morning in early winter, I
                felt her absence.</p>
        <p>It was
                still dark, between six and seven o’clock. The house was cold. I pulled on the big
                woolly brown bathrobe that Queenie and I shared. We called it Buffalo Bill and
                whichever of us got out of bed first in the morning would grab it. A mystery
                where it came from. ‘Maybe a friend of Bet’s before she married your Dad,’
                Queenie said. ‘But don’t say anything, she’d kill me.’</p>
        <p>Her bed was
                empty and she wasn’t in the bathroom. I went down the stairs not turning any lights
                on, not wanting to wake Bet. I looked out the little window in the front door. The
                hard pavement, the sidewalk, and the flat grass in the front yard all
                glittering with frost. The snow was late. I turned up the hall thermostat and
                the furnace rolled over in the dark, gave its reliable growl. We had just got
                the oil furnace and my father said he still woke up at five every
                morning, thinking it was time to go down to the cellar and build up the
                fire.</p>
        <p>My father
                slept in what had been a pantry, off the kitchen. He had an iron bed and a
                broken-backed chair he kept his stack of old National Geographies on, to read when he couldn’t sleep. He turned the ceiling
                light off and on by a cord tied to the bed-frame. This whole arrangement seemed
                to me quite natural and proper for the man of the house, the father. He should sleep
                like a sentry with a coarse blanket for cover and an unhousebroken smell about
                him, of engines and tobacco. Reading and wakeful till all hours and alert all
                through his sleep.</p>
        <p>Even so, he
                hadn’t heard Queenie. He said she must be somewhere in the house. ‘Did you look in
                the bathroom?’</p>
        <p>I said,
                ‘She’s not there.’</p>
        <p>‘Maybe in
                with her mother. Case of the heebie-jeebies.’</p>
        <p>My father
                called it the heebie-jeebies when Bet woke up - or didn’t quite wake up - from a bad
                dream. She would come blundering out of her room unable to say what had frightened
                her, and Queenie had to be the one to guide her back to bed. Queenie would curl
                against her back making comforting noises like a puppy lapping milk, and Bet
                would not remember anything in the morning.</p>
        <p>I had
                turned the kitchen light on.</p>
        <p>‘I didn’t
                want to wake her,’ I said. ‘Bet.’</p>
        <p>I looked at
                the rusty-bottomed bread tin swiped too often by the dishcloth, and the pots sitting
                on the stove, washed but not put away, and the motto supplied by Fairholme Dairy:
                The Lord is the Heart of Our House. All these things stupidly waiting for the
                day to begin and not knowing that it had been hollowed out by
                catastrophe.</p>
        <p>The door to
                the side porch had been unlocked.</p>
        <p>‘Somebody
                came in,’ I said. ‘Somebody came in and took Queenie.’</p>
        <p>My father
                came out with his trousers on over his long underwear. Bet was slapping downstairs
                in her slippers and her chenille robe, flicking on lights as she came.</p>
        <p>‘Queenie
                not in with you?’ my father said. To me he said, ‘The door had to’ve been unlocked
                from the inside.’</p>
        <p>Bet said,
                ‘What’s this about Queenie?’</p>
        <p>‘She might
                just have felt like a walk,’ my father said.</p>
        <p>Bet ignored
                this. She had a mask of some pink stuff dried on her face. She never sold any
                cosmetic she had not tried on herself.</p>
        <p>‘You get
                over to Vorguilla’s,’ she said to me. ‘She might’ve thought of something she was
                supposed to do over there.’</p>
        <p>This was a
                week or so after Mrs Vorguilla’s funeral, but Queenie had
                kept on working there, helping to box up dishes and linens so that Mr Vorguilla
                could move into an apartment. He had the Christmas concerts to get ready for
                and could not do all the packing himself. Bet wanted Queenie to just quit, so
                that she could get taken on for Christmas help at one of the stores.</p>
        <p>I put on my
                father’s rubber boots that were by the door, instead of going upstairs for my shoes.
                I stumbled across the yard to the Vorguillas’ porch and rang the bell. It was a
                chime that seemed to proclaim the musicality of the household. I hugged Buffalo
                Bill tight around me and prayed. Oh, Queenie, Queenie, turn the lights on. I
                forgot that if Queenie was working in there, the lights would be on
                already.</p>
        <p>No answer.
                I pounded on the wood. Mr Vorguilla was going to be in a bad temper when I finally
                woke him. I pressed my head to the door, listening for stirrings.</p>
        <p>‘Mr
                Vorguilla. Mr Vorguilla. I’m sorry to wake you, Mr Vorguilla. Is anybody
                home?’</p>
        <p>A window
                was heaved up in the house on the other side of the Vorguillas’. Mr Hovey, an old
                bachelor, lived there with his sister.</p>
        <p>‘Use your
                eyes,’ Mr Hovey called down. ‘Look in the driveway.’</p>
        <p>Mr
                Vorguilla’s car was gone.</p>
        <p>Mr Hovey
                slammed down the window.</p>
        <p>When I
                opened our kitchen door I saw my father and Bet sitting at the table with cups of
                tea in front of them. For a minute I thought that order had been restored. There had
                been a phone call, perhaps, with some pacifying news.</p>
        <p>‘Mr
                Vorguilla isn’t there,’ I said. ‘His car’s gone.’</p>
        <p>‘Oh, we know
                that,’ Bet said. ‘We know all about that.’</p>
        <p>My father said, ‘Look at here,’ and pushed a
                piece of paper across the table.</p>
        <p>‘I am going to marry Mr Vorguilla,’ it said.
                ‘Yours truly, Queenie.’</p>
        <p>‘Underneath the sugar bowl,’ said my
                father.</p>
        <p>Bet dropped her spoon.</p>
        <p>‘I want him prosecuted,’ she shouted. ‘I want
                her in reform school. I want the police.’</p>
        <p>My father
                said, ‘She’s 18 years old and she can get married if she wants to. The police aren’t
                going to set up a road-block.’</p>
        <p>‘Who says
                they’re on the road? They’re shacked up in some motel. That fool of a girl and that
                bugeyed pickle-ass.’ ‘Talk like that isn’t going to bring her back.’ ‘I don’t
                want her back. Not if she comes crawling. She’s made her bed and she can lie in it,
                with her bug-eyed bugger. He can screw her in the ear for all I
            care.’</p>
        <p>My father
                said, ‘That’s enough.’</p>
        <p>Queenie
                brought me a couple of 222s to
                take with my Coke. ‘It’s amazing how your cramps clear up,’ she said. ‘It’s a
                benefit of being married.’</p>
        <p>‘Your Dad
                went and told you,’ she said. ‘He told you about us.’</p>
        <p>When I told
                my father I wanted to get a summer job, before entering Teachers’ College in the
                fall, he had said that maybe I should go to Toronto and look up Queenie. He told me
                that she had written to him in care of his trucking business, asking if he
                could let them have some money to tide them over the winter.</p>
        <p>‘I would’ve
                never had to write to him,’ Queenie said, ‘if Stan hadn’t got sick last year with
                pneumonia.’</p>
        <p>I said, ‘It
                was the first I knew where you were.’ Tears came into my eyes, I didn’t know why.
                Because I’d felt so happy when I found out, so lonely before I found out, because I
                wished right now that she would say, ‘Of course, I always meant to get in touch
                with you,’ and she didn’t say it.</p>
        <p>‘Bet
                doesn’t know,’ I said. ‘She thinks I’m on my own.’</p>
        <p>‘I hope
                not,’ Queenie said. ‘I mean I hope she doesn’t know.’</p>
        <p>I had a lot
                of things to tell her, about home. I told her that the trucking firm had gone from
                three vehicles to a dozen, and that Bet had bought a muskrat coat and expanded her
                business, holding Beauty Clinics now in our house. She had fixed over the room
                where my father used to sleep for these purposes, and he had moved his cot and
                the National Geographies to his office - an air force billet he had towed to the trucking
                yard. Sitting at the kitchen table studying for my Senior Matric I had listened
                to Bet say, ‘A skin this delicate, you should never go near it with a washcloth,’
                prior to loading up some raw-faced woman with lotions and creams. And sometimes
                in a no less intense, but less hopeful tone, ‘I’m telling you I had Evil, I had
                Evil living right next door to me and I never suspected it, because you don’t,
                do you? I always think the best of people. Right up till they kick me between
                the eyes.’</p>
        <p>Never the
                words ‘bugger’, ‘screwed’, ‘greasy-prick’, used in private.</p>
        <p>‘That’s
                right,’ the customer would say. ‘I’m the same.’</p>
        <p>Or, ‘You think you know what sorrow is, but
                you don’t know half.’</p>
        <p>Then she’d
                come back from seeing the woman to the door and say. ‘Touch her face in the dark and
                you’d never know the difference from sandpaper, what can
                I do?’</p>
        <p>Queenie
                didn’t seem interested in hearing about these things. And there was not much time
                anyway. Before we had finished our Cokes there were
                quick hard steps on the gravel and Mr Vorguilla came into the
            kitchen.</p>
        <p>‘So look
                who’s here,’ cried Queenie. She half got up, as if to touch him, but he veered
                toward the sink.</p>
        <p>Her voice
                was full of such laughing surprise that I wondered if he had been told anything
                about my letter or the fact that I was on my way.</p>
        <p>‘It’s
                Chrissy,’ she said.</p>
        <p>‘So I see,’
                said Mr Vorguilla. ‘You must like hot weather, Chrissy, if you come to Toronto in
                the summer.’</p>
        <p>‘She’s
                going to look for a job,’ said Queenie.</p>
        <p>‘And do you
                have some qualifications,’ Mr Vorguilla said. ‘Do you have qualifications for
                finding a job in Toronto?’</p>
        <p>Queenie
                said, ‘She’s got her Senior Matric’.</p>
        <p>‘Well let’s
                hope that’s good enough,’ said Mr Vorguilla. He ran a glass of water and drank it
                all down, standing with his back to us. Exactly as he used to do when Mrs Vorguilla
                and Queenie and I were sitting at the kitchen table in that other house, the
                Vorguillas’ house next door. Mr Vorguilla would come in from a practice
                somewhere, or he would be taking a break from teaching a piano lesson in the
                front room. At the sound of his steps Mrs Vorguilla would have given us a
                warning smile. And we all looked down at our Scrabble letters, giving him the
                option of noticing us or not. Sometimes he didn’t. The opening of the cupboard,
                the turning of the tap, the setting of the glass down on the counter, were like
                a series of little explosions. As if he dared anybody to breathe while he was
                there.</p>
        <p>When he
                taught us music at school he was just the same. He came into the classroom with the
                step of a man who had not a minute to lose and he rapped the pointer once and it was
                time to start. Up and down the aisles he strutted with his ears cocked, his
                bulgy blue eyes alert, his expression tense and quarrelsome. At any moment he
                might stop by your desk to listen to your singing, to see if you were faking or
                out of tune. Then he’d bring his head slowly down, his eyes bulging into yours
                and his hands working to shush the other voices, to bring you to your
                shame. And the word was that he was just as much a dictator with his various
                choirs and glee clubs. Yet he was a favourite with his singers, particularly
                with ladies. They knitted him things at Christmas. Socks and mufflers and mitts
                to keep him warm on his trips between school and school and choir and
                choir.</p>
        <p>When Queenie had the run of the house, after Mrs Vorguilla
                got too sick to manage, she fished out of a drawer a knitted object that she flapped
                in front of my face. It had arrived without the name of its donor.</p>
        <p>‘It’s a
                peter-heater,’ Queenie said. ‘Mrs Vorguilla said don’t show it to him, he would just
                get mad. Don’t you know what a peter-heater is?’</p>
        <p>I said,
                ‘Ugh.’ ‘It’s just a joke, she said.</p>
        <p>Both
                Queenie and Mr Vorguilla had to go out to work in the evenings. Mr
                Vorguilla played the piano in a restaurant. He wore a tuxedo. And Queenie had a job
                selling tickets in a movie theatre. The theatre was just a few blocks away, so
                I walked there with her. And when I saw her sitting in the ticket-booth I
                understood that the make-up and the dyed puffed hair
                and the hoop earrings were not so strange after all. Queenie looked like some
                of the girls passing on the street or going in to see the movie with their
                boyfriends. And she looked very much like some of the girls portrayed in the
                posters that surrounded her. She looked to be connected to the world of drama,
                of heated love affairs and dangers, that was being depicted inside on the
                screen.</p>
        <p>She looked
                - in my father’s words - as if she didn’t have to take a back seat to
                anybody.</p>
        <p>‘Why don’t
                you just wander around for a while?’ she had said to me. But I felt conspicuous. I
                couldn’t imagine sitting in a cafe drinking coffee and advertising to the world that
                I had nothing to do and no place to go. Or going into a store and trying on
                clothes that I had no hope of buying. I climbed the hill again. I waved hello
                to the Greek woman calling out her window. I let myself in with Queenie’s
                key.</p>
        <p>I sat on
                the cot in the sun porch. There was nowhere to hang up the clothes I had brought and
                I thought it might not be such a good idea to unpack, anyway. Mr Vorguilla might not
                like to see any sign that I was staying.</p>
        <p>I thought
                that Mr Vorguilla’s looks had changed, just as Queenie’s had. But his had not
                changed, as hers had, in the direction of what seemed to me a hard foreign glamour
                and sophistication. His hair, which had been reddish-grey, was now quite grey,
                and the expression of his face - always ready to flash with outrage at the
                possibility of disrespect or an inadequate performance or just at the fact of
                something in his house not being where it was supposed to be - seemed now to be
                one of more permanent grievance, as if some insult was being offered or bad
                behaviour going unpunished, all the time in front of his eyes.</p>
        <p>I got up
                and walked around the apartment. You can never get a good look at the places people
                live in while they are there.</p>
        <p>The kitchen
                was the nicest room, though too dark. Queenie had ivy growing up around the window
                over the sink, and she had wooden spoons sticking up out of a pretty, handleless
                mug, just the way Mrs Vorguilla used to have them. The living-room had the
                piano in it, the same piano that had been in the other living-room. There was
                one armchair and a bookshelf made with bricks and planks and a record-player
                and a lot of records sitting on the floor. No television. No
                walnut rocking-chairs or tapestry curtains. Not even the floor-lamp with the Japanese scenes on its parchment
                shade. Yet all these things had been moved to Toronto, on a snowy day. I had
                been home at lunchtime and had seen the moving-truck. Bet couldn’t move from
                the front door. Finally she forgot all the dignity she usually liked to show to
                strangers and opened the door and yelled at the moving-men, ‘You go back to
                Toronto and tell him if he ever shows his face around here again he’ll wish he
                hadn’t’.</p>
        <p>The
                moving-men waved cheerfully as if they were used to scenes like this and maybe they
                were. Moving furniture must expose you to a lot of ranting and raging.</p>
        <p>But where
                had everything gone? Sold, I thought. It must have been sold. My father had said
                that it sounded as if Mr Vorguilla was having a hard time getting going down in
                Toronto, in his line of work. And Queenie had said something about ‘getting
                behind’. She would never have written to my father if they hadn’t gotten
                behind.</p>
        <p>They must
                have sold the furniture before she wrote.</p>
        <p>On the
                bookshelf I saw The Encyclopedia of Music, and The World Companion to Opera, and The Lives of the Great Composers. Also the large thin book with the beautiful
                cover - the Rubaiyat of Omar Khayyam -that Mrs Vorguilla often had
                beside her couch.</p>
        <p>There was
                another book with a similarly decorated cover whose exact title I don’t remember.
                Something in the title made me think I might like it. The word ‘flowered’ or
                ‘perfumed’. I opened it up and I can remember well enough the sentence I
                read.</p>
        <p>‘The young
                odalisques in the harim were also instructed in the exquisite use of their
                fingernails.’ Something close to that, at any rate.</p>
        <p>I was not
                sure what an odalisque was, but the word ‘harim’ (why not ‘harem’) gave me a clue.
                And I had to read on, to find out what they were taught to do with their
                fingernails. I read on and on, maybe for an hour, and then let the book fall to
                the floor. I had feelings of excitement, and disgust, and disbelief. Was this
                the sort of thing that really grown-up people took an interest in? Even the
                design on the cover, the pretty vines all curved and twisted, seemed slightly
                hostile and mocking. I picked the book up to put it back in its place and it
                fell open to show the names on the fly-leaf. Stan and Marigold Vorguilla. In a
                feminine handwriting. Stan and Marigold.</p>
        <p>I thought
                of Mrs Vorguilla’s high white forehead and tight little grey-black curls. Her
                pearl-button earrings and blouses that tied with a bow at the neck. She was taller
                by quite a bit than Mr Vorguilla and people thought that was why they did not
                go out together. But it was really because she got out of breath. She got out
                of breath walking upstairs, or hanging the clothes on the line. And finally she
                got out of breath even sitting at the table playing Scrabble.</p>
        <p>At first my
                father would not let us take any money for fetching her groceries or hanging up her
                washing - he said it was only neighbourly.</p>
        <p>Bet said
                she thought she would try laying around and see if people would come and wait on her
                for nothing.</p>
        <p>Then Mr
                Vorguilla came over and negotiated for Queenie to go and work for them. Queenie
                wanted to go because she had failed her year at high school and didn’t want to
                repeat it. At last Bet said all right, but told her she was not to do any
                nursing.</p>
        <p>‘If he’s
                too cheap to hire a nurse that’s not your lookout.’</p>
        <p>Queenie
                said that Mr Vorguilla put out the pills every morning and gave Mrs Vorguilla a
                sponge-bath every evening. He even tried to wash her sheets in the bathtub as if
                there was not such a thing as a washing-machine in the house.</p>
        <p>I thought
                of the times when we would be playing Scrabble in the kitchen and Mr Vorguilla after
                drinking his glass of water would put a hand on Mrs Vorguilla’s shoulder and sigh,
                as if he had come back from a long wearying journey.</p>
        <p>‘Hello
                pet,’ he would say.</p>
        <p>Mrs
                Vorguilla would duck her head to give his hand a dry kiss.</p>
        <p>‘Hello pet,’
                she would say.</p>
        <p>Then he
                would look at us, at Queenie and me, as if our presence did not absolutely
                offend him. ‘Hello you two.’</p>
        <p>Later on Queenie and I would giggle in our
                beds in the dark.</p>
        <p>‘Goodnight pet.’</p>
        <p>‘Goodnight pet.’</p>
        <p>I wished that we could go back to that
                time.</p>
        <p>Except
                for going to the bathroom in the
                morning and sneaking out to put my pad in the garbage pail, I sat on my made-up cot
                in the sun porch until Mr Vorguilla was out of the house. I was afraid he might
                not have any place to go but apparently he did. As soon as he was gone Queenie
                called to me. She had set out a peeled orange and cornflakes and coffee.</p>
        <p>‘And here’s
                the paper,’ she said. ‘I was looking at the Help Wanteds. First though I want to do
                something with your hair. I want to cut some off the back and I want to do it up in
                rollers, okay with you?’</p>
        <p>I said
                okay. Even while I was eating Queenie kept circling me and looking at me, trying to
                work out her idea. Then she got me up on a stool - I was still drinking my
                coffee - and she began to comb and snip.</p>
        <p>‘What kind
                of a job are we looking for, now?’ she said. ‘I saw one at a dry cleaners. At the
                counter. How would that be?’</p>
        <p>I said,
                ‘That’d be fine.’</p>
        <p>‘Are you
                still planning on being a schoolteacher?’ she said.</p>
        <p>I said I
                didn’t know. I had an idea that she might think that a drab sort of
                occupation.</p>
        <p>‘I think
                you should be. You’re smart enough. Teachers get paid more. They get paid more than
                people like me. You’ve got more independence.’</p>
        <p>But it was
                all right, she said, working at the movie theatre. She had got the job a month or so
                before last Christmas and she was really happy then because she had her own money at
                last and could buy the ingredients for a Christmas cake. And she became friends
                with a man who was selling Christmas trees off the back of a truck. He let her
                have one for fifty cents, and she hauled it up the hill herself. She hung
                streamers of red and green crepe paper, which was cheap. She made some
                ornaments out of silver foil on cardboard and bought others on the day before
                Christmas when they went on sale in the drugstore. She made cookies and hung
                them on the tree as she had seen in a magazine. It was a European
                custom.</p>
        <p>She wanted
                to have a party but she didn’t know who to ask. There were the Greek people, and
                Stan had a couple of friends. Then she got the idea of asking his
            students.</p>
        <p>I still
                couldn’t get used to her saying ‘Stan’. It wasn’t just the reminder of her intimacy
                with Mr Vorguilla. It was that, of course. But it was also the feeling it gave, that
                she had made him up from scratch. A new person. Stan. As if there had never
                been a Mr Vorguilla, that we had known together - let alone a Mrs Vorguilla -
                in the first place.</p>
        <p>Stan’s
                students were all adults by that time - he really preferred adults to schoolchildren
                - so they didn’t have to worry about the sort of games and entertainment you plan
                for children. They held the party on a Sunday evening, because all the other
                evenings were taken up with Stan’s work at the restaurant and Queenie’s at the
                theatre.</p>
        <p>The Greeks brought wine they had made and some of the
                students brought eggnog mix and rum and sherry. And some brought records you could
                dance to. They had thought that Stan wouldn’t have any records of that kind of
                music and they were right.</p>
        <p>Queenie
                made sausage-rolls and gingerbread and the Greek woman brought her own kind of
                cookies. Everything was good. The party was a success. Queenie danced with a Chinese
                boy named Andrew, who had brought a record she loved.</p>
        <p>‘Turn,
                turn, turn,’ she said, and I moved my head as directed. She laughed and said, ‘No,
                no, I didn’t mean you. That’s the record. That’s the song. It’s by the
                Byrds.’</p>
        <p>‘Turn,
                turn, turn,’ she sang. ‘To everything, there is a season -’</p>
        <p>Andrew was
                a dentistry student. But he wanted to learn to play the Moonlight Sonata. Stan said
                that was going to take him a long time. Andrew was patient. He told Queenie that he
                could not afford to go home for Christmas. His home was in Northern
                Ontario.</p>
        <p>‘I thought
                he was from China,’ I said.</p>
        <p>‘No, not
                Chinese Chinese. From here.’</p>
        <p>They did
                play one children’s game. They played musical chairs. Everybody was boisterous by
                that time. Even Stan. He pulled Queenie down into his lap when she was running past,
                and he wouldn’t let her go. And then when everybody had gone he wouldn’t let
                her clean up. He just wanted her to come to bed.</p>
        <p>‘You know
                the way men are,’ Queenie said. ‘Do you have a boyfriend yet, or
            anything?’</p>
        <p>I said no. The last man my father had hired as a driver was
                always coming to the house to deliver some unimportant message, and my father said,
                ‘He just wants a chance to talk to Chrissy.’ I was cool to him, however, and so
                far he hadn’t got up the nerve to ask me out. I didn’t want to go out with
                anybody from home.</p>
        <p>‘So you
                don’t really know about that stuff yet?’ said Queenie.</p>
        <p>I said, ‘Of
                course I know.’</p>
        <p>‘You don’t sound like you do,’ she
                said.</p>
        <p>The guests at the party had eaten up nearly
                everything but the cake. They did not eat much of that but Queenie wasn’t offended.
                It was very rich, and by the time they got to it they were filled up with
                sausage-rolls and other things. Also, it had not had time to ripen the way the book
                said it should, so she was just as glad to have some left over. She was
                thinking, before Stan pulled her away, that she should get the cake wrapped up
                in a wine-soaked cloth and put it in a cool place.</p>
        <p>She was either thinking of doing that or she had actually
                done it, and in the morning she saw that the cake was not on the table so she
                thought she had done it. She thought good, the cake was put away.</p>
        <p>A day or so
                later Stan said, ‘Let’s have a piece of that cake.’ She said oh, let it ripen a bit
                more, but he insisted. She went to the cupboard and then to the refrigerator, but it
                was not there. She looked high and low and she could not find it. She thought
                back to seeing it on the table. And a memory came to her, of getting a clean
                cloth and soaking it in wine and wrapping that carefully around the leftover
                cake. And then of wrapping waxed paper around the outside of the cloth. But when
                had she done that? Had she done it at all or only dreamed about it? Where had
                she put the cake when she finished wrapping it? She tried to see herself
                putting it away but her mind went blank.</p>
        <p>She looked
                all through the cupboard, but she knew the cake was too big to be hidden there. Then
                she looked in the oven and even in insane places like her dresser drawers and under
                the bed and on the closet shelf. It was nowhere.</p>
        <p>‘If you put
                it somewhere, then it must be somewhere,’ Stan said.</p>
        <p>‘I did. I
                put it somewhere,’ said Queenie.</p>
        <p>‘Maybe you
                were drunk and you threw it out.’</p>
        <p>She said, ‘I wasn’t drunk. I didn’t throw it
                out.’</p>
        <p>But she went
                and looked in the garbage. No.</p>
        <p>He sat at
                the table watching her. If you put it somewhere it must be somewhere. She was
                getting frantic.</p>
        <p>‘Are you
                sure?’ said Stan. ‘Are you sure you didn’t just give it away?’</p>
        <p>She was
                sure. She was sure she hadn’t given it away. She had wrapped it up to keep. She was
                sure, she was almost sure she had wrapped it to keep. She was sure she had not given
                it away.</p>
        <p>‘Oh, I
                don’t know about that,’ Stan said. ‘I think maybe you gave it away. And I think I
                know who to.’</p>
        <p>Queenie was
                brought to a standstill. Who to?</p>
        <p>‘I think
                you gave it to Andrew.’</p>
        <p>To
                Andrew?</p>
        <p>Oh yes.
                Poor Andrew who was telling her he couldn’t afford to go home for Christmas. She was
                sorry for Andrew.</p>
        <p>‘So you gave
                him our cake.’</p>
        <p>No, said
                Queenie. Why would she do that? She would not do that. She had never thought of
                giving Andrew the cake.</p>
        <p>Stan said,
                ‘Lena. Don’t lie.’</p>
        <p>That was
                the beginning of Queenie’s long miserable struggle. All she could say was no. No,
                no, I did not give the cake to anybody. I did not give the cake to Andrew. I am not
                lying. No. No.</p>
        <p>‘Probably
                you were drunk,’ Stan said. ‘You were drunk and you are not remembering very
                well.’</p>
        <p>Queenie said
                she was not drunk.</p>
        <p>‘You were the one who was drunk,’ she
                said.</p>
        <p>He got up
                and came at her with his hand raised, saying not to tell him that he’d been drunk,
                never to tell him that.</p>
        <p>Queenie
                cried out, ‘I won’t. I won’t. I’m sorry.’ And he didn’t hit her. But she began to
                cry. She kept crying while she tried to persuade him. Why would she give away the
                cake she had worked so hard to make? Why would he not believe her? Why would
                she lie to him?</p>
        <p>‘Everybody
                lies,’ Stan said. And the more she cried and begged him to believe her, the more
                cool and sarcastic he became.</p>
        <p>‘Use a
                little logic,’ he said. ‘If it’s here, get up and find it. If it isn’t here, then
                you gave it away.’</p>
        <p>Queenie
                said that wasn’t logic. It did not have to be given away, just because she could not
                find it. Then he came close to her again in such a calm
                half-smiling way that she thought for a moment he was going to kiss her.
                Instead he closed his hands around her throat and just for a second cut off her
                breath. He didn’t even leave any marks.</p>
        <p>‘Now,’ he
                said. ‘Now - are you going to teach me about logic?’</p>
        <p>Then he
                went to get dressed to go and play at the restaurant.</p>
        <p>He stopped
                speaking to her. He wrote her a note saying he would speak to her again when she
                told the truth. All over Christmas she could not stop crying. She and Stan were
                supposed to go and visit the Greek people on Christmas day but she couldn’t go,
                her face was such a mess. Stan had to go and say that she was sick. The Greek
                people probably knew the truth anyway. They had probably heard the hullabaloo
                through the walls.</p>
        <p>She put on
                a ton of make-up and went to work and the manager said, ‘You want to give the people
                the idea this is a tragedy?’ She said she had infected sinuses and he let her go
                home.</p>
        <p>When Stan
                came home that night and pretended she didn’t exist she turned over and looked at
                him. She knew that he would get into bed and lie beside her like a post and that if
                she moved against him he would continue to lie like a post until she moved
                away. She saw that he could go on living like this and she could not. She
                thought that if she had to go on in this way she would die. Just as if he
                really had choked off her breath, she would die.</p>
        <p>So she said,
                forgive me.</p>
        <p>Forgive me.
                I did what you said. I’m sorry.</p>
        <p>Please.
                Please. I’m sorry.</p>
        <p>He sat down
                on the bed. He didn’t say anything.</p>
        <p>She said
                that she had really forgotten about giving the cake away but that now she remembered
                that she had done it and she was sorry.</p>
        <p>‘I wasn’t
                lying,’ she said. ‘I forgot.’</p>
        <p>‘You forgot
                you gave the cake to Andrew?’ he said.</p>
        <p>‘I must
                have. I forgot.’</p>
        <p>‘To Andrew.
                You gave it to Andrew.’</p>
        <p>Yes,
                Queenie said. Yes, yes, that was what she had done. And she began to howl and hang
                on to him and beg him to forgive her.</p>
        <p>All right,
                stop the hysterics, he said. He did not say that he forgave her but he got a warm
                washcloth and wiped her face and lay down beside her and cuddled her and pretty soon
                he wanted to do everything else.</p>
        <p>‘No more
                music lessons for Mr Moonlight Sonata,’ he finally said.</p>
        <p>What a
                relief.</p>
        <p>And then to top it all off, later she found
                the cake.</p>
        <p>She found it
                wrapped up in a dishtowel and then wrapped in waxed paper just as she had
                remembered. And put into a shopping bag and hung from a hook in the back porch. Of
                course. The sun porch was the ideal place because it got too cold to use in
                winter, but it wasn’t freezing cold. She must have been thinking that when she
                hung the cake there. That this was the ideal place. And then she forgot. She
                was a little drunk - she had to be. She had forgotten absolutely. And there it
                was.</p>
        <p>She found
                it, and she threw it all out. She never told Stan.</p>
        <p>‘I pitched
                it,’ she said. ‘It was just as good as ever and all that expensive fruit and stuff
                in it but there was no way I wanted to get that subject brought up again. So I just
                pitched it out.’</p>
        <p>Her voice
                which had been so woeful in the bad parts of the story was now sly and full of
                laughter, as if all the time she had been telling me a joke, and throwing out the
                cake was the final, ridiculous point of it.</p>
        <p>I had to
                pull my head out of her hands and turn around and look at her.</p>
        <p>I said, ‘But
                he was wrong.’ ‘Well of course he was wrong,’ she said. ‘Men are not normal,
                Chrissy. That’s one thing you’ll learn if you ever get married.’</p>
        <p>‘I never
                will then,’ I said. ‘I never will get married.’</p>
        <p>‘He was
                just jealous,’ she said. ‘He was just so jealous.’</p>
        <p>‘Never,’ I
                said.</p>
        <p>‘Well you
                and me are very different, Chrissy. Very different’.
                She sighed. She said, ‘I am a creature of love.’</p>
        <p>I thought
                that you might see these words on a movie poster. A creature of love. Maybe on a
                poster of one of the movies that had played at Queenie’s theatre.</p>
        <p>‘You are
                going to look so good when I take these rollers out,’ she said. ‘You won’t be saying
                you haven’t got a boyfriend for very long.’</p>
        <p>‘But it’ll be too late to go looking today,’ she said. ‘Early
                bird tomorrow. If Stan asks you anything say you went to a couple of places and they
                took your phone number. Say a store or a restaurant or anything just so long as
                he thinks you’re looking.’</p>
        <p>I was hired the next day at the first place I tried, though I hadn’t
                managed to be such an early bird after all. Queenie had decided to do my hair still
                another way and to make up my eyes, but the result was not what she had hoped
                for. ‘You’re really more the natural type after all,’ she said, and I scrubbed
                it all off and put on my own red lipstick.</p>
        <p>By this
                time it was too late for Queenie to go out with me, to check on her Post Office box.
                She had to get ready to go to the movie theatre. It was a Saturday, so she had to
                work in the afternoon as well as in the evening. She got out her key and asked
                me to check the box for her, as a favour. She explained to me where it
                was.</p>
        <p>‘I had to
                get my own box when I wrote to your Dad,’ she said.</p>
        <p>The job
                I got was in a drugstore in the
                basement of an apartment building. I was hired to work behind the lunch counter.
                When I first came in I felt fairly hopeless. My hairstyle was drooping in the
                heat and I had a moustache of sweat on my upper lip. At least my cramps had
                moderated.</p>
        <p>A woman in
                a white uniform was at the counter, drinking coffee.</p>
        <p>‘Did you
                come about the job?’ she said.</p>
        <p>I said yes. The woman had a hard square face,
                pencilled eyebrows, a beehive of purplish hair.</p>
        <p>‘You speak
                English, do you?’</p>
        <p>‘Yes.’ ‘I
                mean you didn’t just learn it? You’re not a foreigner?’</p>
        <p>I said I
                wasn’t.</p>
        <p>‘I tried
                out two girls in the last two days and I had to let them both go. One let on she
                could speak English but she couldn’t and the other I had to tell her everything ten
                times over. Wash your hands good at the sink and I’ll get you an apron. My
                husband is the pharmacist and I do the till.’ (I noticed for the first time a
                grey-haired man behind a high counter in the corner, looking at me
                and pretending not to.) ‘It’s slow now but it’ll get busy in a while. It’s all
                old people in this block and after their naps they start coming down here
                wanting coffee.’</p>
        <p>I tied on an apron and took my place behind the counter.
                Hired for a job in Toronto. I tried to find out
                where things were without asking questions and had to ask only two - how to work the
                coffee-maker and what to do about the money.</p>
        <p>‘You make
                out the bill and they bring it to me. What did you think?’</p>
        <p>It was all
                right. People came in one or two at a time mostly wanted coffee or a Coke. I kept
                the cups washed and wiped the counter clean and apparently I made out the bills
                properly as there was no complaint. The customers were mostly old people as the
                woman had said. Some spoke to me in a kindly way, saying I was new here and
                even asking where I came from. Others seemed to be in a kind of trance. One
                woman wanted toast and I managed that. Then I did a ham sandwich. There was a
                little flurry with four people there at once. A man wanted pie and ice-cream and I
                found the ice-cream hard as cement to scoop out. But I did it. I got more
                confident. I said to them, ‘Here you are,’ when I set down their orders, and
                ‘Here’s the damage,’ when I presented the bill.</p>
        <p>In a slow
                moment the woman from the till came over.</p>
        <p>‘I see you
                made somebody toast,’ she said. ‘Can you read?’</p>
        <p>She pointed to a sign stuck on the mirror
                behind the counter.</p>
        <p>No Breakfast Items served after 11
            a.m.</p>
        <p>I said that I thought it was okay to make
                toast, if you could make toasted sandwiches.</p>
        <p>‘Well you
                thought wrong. Toasted sandwiches yes, ten cents extra. Toast, no. Do you understand
                now?’</p>
        <p>I said yes.
                I wasn’t so crushed as I might have been at first. All the time I was working I
                thought what a relief it would be to go back and tell Mr Vorguilla that yes, I had a
                job. Now I could go and look for a room of my own to live in. Maybe tomorrow,
                Sunday, if the drugstore was closed. If I even had one room, I thought, Queenie
                would have some place to run away to if Mr Vorguilla got mad at her again. And
                if Queenie ever decided to leave Mr Vorguilla (I persisted in thinking of
                this as a possibility in spite of how Queenie had finished her story) then with
                the pay from both our jobs maybe we could get a little apartment. Or at least a
                room with a hotplate and a toilet and shower to ourselves. It would be like
                when we lived at home with our parents except that our parents would be
                away.</p>
        <p>I garnished
                each sandwich with a bit of torn off lettuce and a dill pickle. That was what
                another sign on the mirror promised. But when I got the dill pickle out of a jar I
                thought it looked like too much so I cut it in half. I had just served a man a
                sandwich in this way when the woman from the till came over and got herself a
                cup of coffee. She took her coffee back
                to the till and drank it</p>
        <p>standing up.
                When the man had finished his sandwich and paid for it and left the store she came
                over again.</p>
        <p>‘You gave
                that man half a dill pickle. Have you been doing that with every
            sandwich?’</p>
        <p>I said
                yes.</p>
        <p>‘Don’t you know how to slice a pickle? One
                pickle ought to last ten sandwiches.’</p>
        <p>I looked at the sign. I said, ‘It doesn’t say
                a slice. It says a pickle.’</p>
        <p>‘That’s
                enough,’ the woman said. ‘Get out of that apron. I don’t take any back talk from my
                employees, that’s one thing I don’t take. You can get your purse and get out of
                here. And don’t go asking me where’s your pay because you haven’t been any use
                to me anyway and this was just supposed to be training.’</p>
        <p>The
                grey-haired man was peeking out again, with a faint smile.</p>
        <p>So I found myself out on the street again, walking to the
                streetcar stop. But I knew the way some streets went now and I knew how to use a
                transfer. I had even had experience at a job. I could say that I had worked
                behind a lunch counter. If anybody wanted a reference it would be tricky - but
                I could say the lunch counter was in my home town. While I waited for the
                streetcar I took out the list of other places where I meant to apply, and the
                map that Queenie had given me. But it was later than I’d thought and most
                places seemed too far away. I dreaded having to tell Mr Vorguilla. I decided to
                walk back, in the hopes that when I got there he’d have gone.</p>
        <p>I had just
                turned up the hill when I remembered the Post Office. I found my way back to it and
                got a letter out of the box and walked home again. Surely he would be gone by now, I
                thought.</p>
        <p>But he
                wasn’t. When I walked past the open living-room window that overlooked the path
                beside the house, I heard music. It wasn’t what Queenie would play. It was the sort
                of complicated music that we had heard sometimes coming through the open
                windows of the Vorguillas’ house - music that demanded your attention and then
                didn’t go anywhere, or at least didn’t go anywhere fast enough.
                Classical.</p>
        <p>Queenie was
                in the kitchen, wearing another of her skimpy dresses, and all her make-up. She had
                bangles on her arms. She was setting tea-cups on a tray. I was dizzy for a moment
                coming out of the sunlight, and every inch of my skin bloomed with
                sweat.</p>
        <p>‘Shh,’
                Queenie said, because I’d closed the door with a crash. ‘They’re in there listening
                to records. It’s him and his friend Leslie.’</p>
        <p>Just as she
                said this the music came to an abrupt halt and there was a burst of excited
                talk.</p>
        <p>‘One of
                them plays a record and the other has to guess what it is just from a little bit of
                it,’ Queenie said. ‘They play these little bits and then stop, over and over. It
                drives you crazy.’ She started cutting slices off a delicatessen chicken and
                putting them on buttered slices of bread. ‘Did you get a job?’ she
            said.</p>
        <p>‘Yes but it
                wasn’t permanent.’ ‘Oh well.’ She didn’t seem very interested. But as the music
                started again she looked up and smiled and said, ‘Did you go to the -’ And she
                saw the letter I was carrying in my hand.</p>
        <p>She dropped
                the knife and came to me in a hurry, saying softly, ‘You walked right in with it in
                your hand, I should have told you, put it in your purse. My private letter.’ She
                grabbed it from my hand and right at that moment the kettle on the stove began
                to shriek.</p>
        <p>‘Oh, get
                the kettle,’ she said. ‘Chrissy, quick, quick. Get the kettle or he’ll be out here,
                he can’t stand the sound.’</p>
        <p>She had
                turned her back and was tearing open the envelope.</p>
        <p>I took the
                kettle off the burner, and she said, ‘Make the tea, please -’ in the soft
                preoccupied voice of somebody reading an urgent message.</p>
        <p>‘Is it in
                the pot?’ I said.</p>
        <p>‘Yes, yes,
                just pour the water on, it’s measured.’ She laughed as if my asking her that was a
                joke. I poured the water on the tealeaves and she said, ‘Thanks. Oh, thanks,
                Chrissy, thanks.’ She turned around and looked at me. Her face was rosy and all
                the bangles on her arms jingled with a delicate agitation. She folded up the
                letter and pulled up her skirt and tucked it under the elastic waistband of her
                underpants.</p>
        <p>She said,
                ‘Sometimes he goes through my purse.’</p>
        <p>I said, ‘Is
                the tea for them?’</p>
        <p>‘Yes. And I
                have to get back to work. Oh, what am I doing? I have to cut the sandwiches. Where’s
                the knife?’</p>
        <p>I picked up
                the knife and cut the sandwiches and put them on a plate.</p>
        <p>‘Don’t you
                want to know who my letter’s from?’ she said.</p>
        <p>I couldn’t
                think. I still had the sensation of the room moving around me, though it wasn’t
                doing that any more in a physical way.</p>
        <p>I said,
                ‘Bet?’</p>
        <p>Because I
                had a hope that a private forgiveness from Bet could be the thing that had made
                Queenie burst into flower.</p>
        <p>I had not
                even looked at the writing on the envelope.</p>
        <p>Queenie’s
                face changed, her mouth curled, and she said, ‘Hardly.’ Then she recovered her
                happiness. She came and put her arms around me and spoke into my ear, in a voice
                that was shivering and shy and triumphant. ‘It’s from Andrew,’ she said. ‘Can
                you take the tray in to them. I can’t. I can’t right now. Oh, thank
                you.’</p>
        <p>Before
                Queenie went off to work she came into the living-room and kissed
                both Mr Vorguilla and his friend. She kissed both of them on their foreheads. She
                gave me a butterfly wave and said, ‘Bye bye.’</p>
        <p>When I had
                brought the tray in I saw the annoyance on Mr Vorguilla’s face, that it wasn’t
                Queenie. But he spoke to me in a surprisingly tolerant way and introduced me to
                Leslie. Leslie was a stout bald man who at first looked to me almost as old as
                Mr Vorguilla, but when you got used to him and took his baldness into account
                he looked much younger. He was not the sort of friend I would have expected Mr
                Vorguilla to have. He was not brusque or know-it-all but comfortable and full
                of encouragement. For example, when I told about my employment at the lunch
                counter he said, ‘Well you know, that’s something. Getting hired the
                first place you tried. It shows you know how to make a
                good impression.’</p>
        <p>I had not
                found the experience hard to talk about. The presence of Leslie made everything
                easier and seemed to soften the behaviour of Mr Vorguilla. As if he had to show me a
                decent courtesy in the presence of his friend. It could also have been that he
                sensed a change in me. People do sense the difference, when you are not afraid
                of them any more. He would not be sure of this difference and he would have no
                idea how it came about, but it would puzzle him and make him more careful. He
                agreed with Leslie when Leslie said I was well out of that job and he even went on
                to say that the woman sounded like the sort of hard-bitten chiseller you
                sometimes found in that kind of hole-in-corner establishment in
            Toronto.</p>
        <p>‘And she
                had no business not paying you,’ he said.</p>
        <p>‘You’d
                think the husband might have come forward,’ said Leslie. ‘If he was the druggist, he
                was the boss.’</p>
        <p>‘He ought
                to brew up a special dose,’ Mr Vorguilla said. ‘For his wife.’</p>
        <p>It wasn’t
                so hard to pour out tea and offer milk and sugar and pass sandwiches, and even talk,
                when you knew something other people didn’t know, about a danger they were in. It
                was just because he didn’t know that I could feel something other than loathing
                for Mr Vorguilla. It wasn’t that he had changed in himself - or if he had
                changed it was probably because I had. I had changed enough to feel now almost
                less uneasy with him than I would have to feel with Queenie.</p>
        <p>Mr
                Vorguilla soon said that it was time for him to go to work. He went to change his
                clothes. Then Leslie asked me if I would like to have supper with him.</p>
        <p>‘Just
                around the corner there’s a place I go,’ he said. ‘Nothing fancy. Nothing like
                Stan’s place.’</p>
        <p>I was glad
                enough to hear that it wouldn’t be any place fancy. I said, ‘Sure.’ And after we had
                dropped off Mr Vorguilla at the restaurant we drove in Leslie’s car to a fish and
                chips place. Leslie ordered the Super Dinner - though he had just consumed
                several chicken sandwiches - and I ordered the Regular. He had a beer and I had
                a Coke.</p>
        <p>He talked
                about himself. He said he wished he had gone to Teachers’ College himself instead of
                choosing music which did not make for a very settled life.</p>
        <p>I was too
                absorbed in my own situation even to ask him what kind of musician he was. My father
                had bought me a return ticket, saying, ‘You never know how things are going to sit
                with him and her.’ I had thought of that ticket at the moment I watched Queenie
                tucking Andrew’s letter under the fold of her underpants. Even though I didn’t
                yet know that it was Andrew’s letter.</p>
        <p>I hadn’t
                just come to Toronto, or come to Toronto to get a summer job. I had come to be part
                of Queenie’s life, or if necessary, part of Queenie’s and Mr Vorguilla’s life. Even
                when I had the fantasy about Queenie living with me, the fantasy had something
                to do with Mr Vorguilla and how she would be serving him right.</p>
        <p>And when
                I’d thought of the return ticket I was taking something else for granted. That I
                could go back and live with Bet and my father and be part of their life.</p>
        <p>My father
                and Bet. Mr and Mrs Vorguilla. Queenie and Mr Vorguilla. Even Queenie and Andrew.
                These were couples and each of them, however disjointed, had now or in memory a
                private burrow with its own heat and confusion, from which I was cut off. And I
                had to be, I wished to be, cut off, for there was nothing I could see in their
                lives to instruct me or encourage me.</p>
        <p>Leslie too
                was a person cut off. Yet he talked to me about various people he was connected to
                by ties of blood or friendship. His sister and her husband. His nieces and nephews,
                the married couples he visited and spent holidays with. There was not one of
                these people he did not see in a fairly sunny light. All had problems but all
                had value. He talked about their jobs, lack of jobs, talents, strokes of luck,
                errors in judgment, with great interest but a lack of passion. He was cut off,
                or so he appeared to be, from love or vengefulness.</p>
        <p>I would have
                seen flaws in this, later in my life. I would have felt the impatience, even
                suspicion, a woman can feel towards a man who lacks a motive. Who has only
                friendship to offer and offers that so easily and bountifully that even if it
                is rejected he can move along as buoyantly as ever.</p>
        <p>Here was no
                solitary fellow hoping to hook up with a girl. Even I could see that, inexperienced
                as I was. Just a person who took comfort in the moment and in a sort of reasonable
                fagade of life.</p>
        <p>His company
                was just what I needed at the moment, though I hardly realised it. Probably he was
                being deliberately kind to me. As I had thought of myself being kind to Mr
                Vorguilla, or at least protecting him, so unexpectedly, a little while
                before.</p>
        <p>I was at Teachers’ College when Queenie ran away again. I got the
                news in a letter from my father. He said that he did not know just how or when it
                happened. Mr Vorguilla hadn’t let him know for a while, and then he had, in
                case Queenie had come back home. My father had told Mr Vorguilla he didn’t
                think there was much chance of that. In the letter to me he said that at least
                it wasn’t now the kind of thing we would say Queenie wouldn’t do.</p>
        <p>For years,
                even after I was married, I would get a Christmas card from Mr Vorguilla. Sleighs
                laden with bright parcels; a happy family in a decorated doorway, welcoming friends.
                Perhaps he thought these were the sort of scenes that would appeal to me, in my
                present way of life. Or perhaps he picked them blindly off the rack. He always
                included a return address, reminding me of his existence and letting me know
                where he was, in case of any news.</p>
        <p>I had given
                up expecting that kind of news. I never even found out if it was Andrew Queenie went
                away with, or somebody else. Or whether she stayed with Andrew, if he was the one.
                When my father died there was some money left, and a serious attempt was made
                to trace her, but without success.</p>
        <p>But now
                something has happened. Now in the years when my children are grown up and my
                husband has retired, and he and I are travelling a lot, I have an idea that
                sometimes I see Queenie. It’s not through any particular wish or effort that I
                see her, and it’s not as if I believed it was really her, either.</p>
        <p>Once it was
                in a crowded airport, and she was wearing a sarong and a flower-trimmed straw hat.
                Tanned and excited, rich-looking, surrounded by friends. And once she was among the
                women at a church door waiting for a glimpse of the wedding party. She wore a
                spotty suede jacket that time, and she did not look either prosperous or well.
                Another time she was stopped at a crosswalk, leading a string of nursery-school
                children on their way to the swimming-pool or the park. It was a hot day and
                her thick middle-aged figure was frankly and comfortably on view, in flowered
                shorts and a sloganed T-shirt.</p>
        <p>The last
                and the strangest time was in a supermarket in Twin Falls, Idaho. I came around a
                corner carrying the few things I had collected for a picnic lunch, and there was an
                old woman leaning on her shopping-cart, as if waiting for me. A little wrinkled
                woman with a crooked mouth and an unhealthy-looking brownish skin. Hair in
                yellow-brown bristles, purple pants hitched up over the small mound of her
                stomach - she was one of those thin women who have nevertheless, with age, lost
                the convenience of a waistline. The pants could have come from some thrift shop and
                so could the gaily coloured but matted and shrunken sweater buttoned over a
                chest no bigger than a ten-year-old’s.</p>
        <p>The
                shopping-cart was empty. She was not even carrying a purse.</p>
        <p>Unlike
                those other women, this one seemed to know that she was Queenie. She smiled at me
                with such merriment of recognition, and such a yearning to be recognised, that you
                would think this was a moment granted to her when she was let out of the
                shadows for one day in a thousand.</p>
        <p>And all I
                did was stretch my mouth at her, as at a loony stranger, and keep on going towards
                the check-out.</p>
        <p>Then in the
                parking lot I made an excuse to my husband, said I’d forgotten something, and
                hurried back into the store. I went up and down the aisles, looking. And in just
                that little time the old woman seemed to have gone. She might have gone out
                right after I did, and be making her way now along the streets of Twin Falls.
                On foot, or in a car driven by some relative or neighbour, or even in a car she
                drove herself. It was possible but hardly likely that she was still in the store,
                and that we kept going up and down the aisles just missing each
            other.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
